Welcome to the final video of this Machine Learning class.
ยินดีต้อนรับสู่วิดีโอสุดท้ายของวิชา Machine Learning
We've been through a lot of different videos together.
เราผ่านกันมาหลากหลายบทเรียนแล้ว
In this video I would like to just quickly
วิดีโอนี้ ผมขอสรุปหัวข้อหลัก
summarize the main topics of this course
ของวิชานี้อย่างรวดเร็ว
and then say a few words at the end and that
แล้วกล่าวอีกเล็กน้อยในตอนจบ
will wrap up the class.
และนั่นก็เป็นการสรุปสำหรับวิชานี้
So what have we done?
เอาล่ะ สิ่งที่เราได้ทำจบนั้นมีอะไรบ้าง
In this class we spent a lot of time talking about supervised learning algorithms
บทเรียนนี้ เราได้ใช้เวลาไปมากกับ supervised learning algorithms
like linear regression, logistic regression, neural networks, SVMs.
อย่างเช่น linear regression, logistic regression, neural networks, SVMs
for problems where you have labelled data and labelled examples
ปัญหาที่ข้อมูลและตัวอย่างมีการระบุชื่อ(labelled)
like x(i), y(i)
อย่างเช่น x(i), y(i)
And we also spent quite a lot of time talking about unsupervised learning
และเราก็ใช้เวลาไม่น้อยไปกับ unsupervised learning
like K-means clustering,
อย่างเช่นเรื่อง K-means clustering,
Principal Components Analysis for dimensionality reduction
Principal Components Analysis ใน dimensionality reduction
and Anomaly Detection algorithms for when you have only
และ Anomaly Detection algorithms เมื่อมีแต่
unlabelled data x(i)
ข้อมูลที่ไม่ระบุชื่อ
Although Anomaly Detection can also use some labelled data
แม้ว่า Anomaly Detection ยังใช้ได้กับข้อมูลที่ระบุชื่อ
to evaluate the algorithm.
เพื่อประเมิน algorithm
We also spent some time talking about special applications
เรายังมีเวลาได้พูดเกี่ยวกับแอพพลิเคชั่นพิเศษ
or special topics like Recommender Systems
หรือหัวข้อพิเศษอย่างเช่น Recommender Systems
and large scale machine learning systems
และ ระบบ machine learning ขนาดใหญ่
including parallelized and rapid-use systems
รวมทั้งระบบ parallelized และ map-reduce
as well as some special applications like
และแอพพลิเคชั่นพิเศษอื่น อย่างเช่น
sliding windows object classification for computer vision.
sliding windows ซึ่งใช้กับ classification วัตถุ ใน computer vision
And finally we also spent a lot of time talking about different aspects
และยังใช้เวลากับหลายเรื่องที่เกี่ยวกับ
of, sort of, advice on building a machine learning system.
คำปรึกษาในการสร้างระบบ machine learning
And this involved both trying to understand
ทั้งเกี่ยวกับการทำความเข้าใจว่า
what is it that makes a machine learning algorithm
อะไรที่ทำให้ machine learning algorithm
work or not work.
ใช้ได้หรือไม่ได้
So we talked about things like bias and variance,
จึงได้พูดเกี่ยวกับ bias และ variance
and how regularization can help with some variance problems.
และการใช้ regularization แก้ปัญหาของ variance
And we also spent a little bit of time talking about
เรายังได้พูดอีกเล็กน้อยว่า
this question of how to decide what to work on next.
เราจะตัดสินใจอย่างไรว่า เราจะต้องทำอะไรต่อ
So, how to prioritize how you spend your time
ดังนั้น การจัดลำดับก่อนหลังว่า เราจะใช้เวล่าอย่างไร
when you're developing a machine learning system.
ในขณะที่กำลังพัฒนาระบบ machine learning
So we talked about evaluation of learning algorithms,
ได้พูดเกี่ยวกับการประเมินผล learning algorithm
evaluation metrics like  precision recall, F1 score
เมตริกซ์ที่ใช้ประเมิน เช่น precision recall, F1 score
as well as practical aspects of evaluation
และการประเมินผลในภาคปฏิบัติ
like the training, cross-validation and test sets.
เช่น trainingt set, cross-validation se และ test set
And we also spent a lot of time talking about
และเราก็ได้ใช้เวลาไปมากในการพูดถึง
debugging learning algorithms and making sure
การแก้ไขจุดบกพร่องใน learning algorithm และ
the learning algorithm is working.
ให้แน่ใจว่า learning algrorithm ใช้งานได้
So we talked about diagnostics
และเรายังพูดถึงการวินิจฉัยต่างๆ
like learning curves and also talked about things like
เช่น learning curve และพูดเรื่องเกี่ยวกับ
error analysis and ceiling analysis.
error analysis และ ceiling analysis
And so all of these were different tools for helping you to decide
เครื่องมือเหล่านี้จะช่วยคุณตัดสินใจ
what to do next and how to spend your valuable
ว่าจะทำอะไรต่อ และควรใช้เวลาอันมีค่าของคุณอย่างไร
time when you're developing a machine learning system.
ในขณะที่กำลังพัฒนาระบบ machine learning
And in addition to having the tools of machine learning at your disposal
นอกเหนือจากการมีเครื่องมือ machine learning พร้อมใช้งานแล้ว
so knowing the tools of machine learning like
การได้รู้จักเครื่องมือต่างๆ ของ machine learning
supervised learning and unsupervised learning and so on,
เช่น supervised learning และ unsupervised learning และอื่นๆ
I hope that you now not only have the tools,
ผมหวังว่า ไม่เพียงมีเครื่องมือเท่านั้น
but that you know how to apply these tools really well
แต่คุณสามารถประยุกต์ใช้เครื่องมือเหล่านี้ได้เป็นอย่างดี
to build powerful machine learning systems.
ในการสร้างระบบ machine learning ที่มีประสิทธิภาพ
So, that's it.
เอาล่ะ จบแล้วครับ
Those were the topics of this class
นั่นก็เป็นหัวข้อต่างๆ ในบทเรียนนี้
and if you worked all the way through this course
และเมื่อคุณได้ทำทุกอย่างตามบทเรียนนี้โดยตลอด
you should now consider yourself
คุณก็สามารถบอกกับตัวเองได้ว่าคุณคือ
an expert in machine learning.
ผู้เชี่ยวชาญ machine learning
As you know, machine learning is a technology
อย่างที่รู้กัน machine learning เป็นเทคโนโลยี
that's having huge impact on science, technology and industry.
ที่มีผลกระทบมากในทางวิทยาศาสตร์ เทคโนโลยี และอุตสาหกรรม
And you're now well qualified to use these tools
และบัดนี้คุณเป็นผู้มีคุณสมบัติเหมาะสมที่จะใช้เครื่องมือ
of machine learning to great effect.
machine learning ที่จะก่อให้เกิดผลอันยิ่งใหญ่ได้
I hope that many of you in this class
ผมหวังว่าพวกคุณในชั้นเรียนนี้
will find ways to use machine learning
จะพบหนทางในการนำ machine learning ไปใช้
to build cool systems and cool applications
ในการสร้างระบบและแอพพลิเคชั่นที่ยอดเยี่ยม
and cool products.
และผลิตภัณฑ์ยอดเยี่ยมด้วย
And I hope that you find ways
และหวังว่าพวกคุณจะพบหนทาง
to use machine learning not only
ในการนำ machine learning ไปใช้ไม่เพียง
to make your life better but maybe someday
ทำให้ชีวิตของคุณดีขึ้น
to use it to make many other people's life better as well.
แต่ยังทำให้ชีวิตผู้อื่นอีกมากมายดีขึ้นด้วย
I also wanted to let you know that this class has been great fun for me to teach.
ผมอยากบอกว่า ผมสนุกในการสอนบทเรียนนี้เป็นอย่างมาก
So, thank you for that.
ขอบคุณด้วยครับ
And before wrapping up,
ก่อนสรุป
there's just one last thing I wanted to say.
สิ่งสุดท้ายที่ผมอยากจะบอก
Which is that: It was maybe not so long ago,
นั่นคือมันอาจไม่นานนัก
that I was a student myself.
ที่ผมเคยเป็นนักศึกษา
And even today, you know, I still try to take different courses
และแม้แต่วันนี้ผมก็ยังคงศึกษาเพิ่มเติมเมื่อมีเวลา
when I have time to try to learn new things.
เพื่อจะได้เรียนรู้สิ่งใหม่
And so I know how time-consuming it is
และผมก็รู้ว่ามันใช้เวลามาก
to learn this stuff.
ที่จะเรียนรู้สิ่งต่างๆ
I know that you're probably a busy person
ผมรู้ว่าเป็นไปได้ที่คุณจะมีงานยุ่ง
with many, many other things going on in your life.
มีสิ่งต่างๆเกิดขึ้นมากมายในชีวิต
And so the fact that you still found
และความเป็นจริงคือคุณก็ยังมี
the time or took the time to watch these videos
เวลาหรือหาเวลาเพื่อดูวิดีโอนี้
and, you know, many of these videos just went on
และวิดีโอที่มากมายเหล่านี้
for hours, right?
ใช้เวลาหลายชั่วโมงทีเดียวใช่ไหมครับ
And the fact many of you took the time
และความเป็นจริงคือคุณก็ใช้เวลา
to go through the review questions
เพื่อศึกษาส่วนที่เป็นคำถามทบทวน
and that many of you took the time
และพวกคุณไม่น้อยที่ใช้เวลา
to work through the programming exercises.
ทำแบบฝึกหัดโปรแกรมมิ่ง
And these were long and complicate programming exercises.
และนั่นก็เป็นแบบฝึกหัดที่ทั้งยาวและยาก
I wanted to say thank you for that.
ผมอยากจะบอกว่าขอบคุณมากครับ
And I know that many of you have worked hard on this class
และผมรู้ว่าคุณได้ศึกษาอย่างหนักในบทเรียนนี้
and that many of you have put a lot of time into this class,
และคุณก็ใช้เวลาไปมากกับบทเรียนนี้
that many of you have put a lot of yourselves into this class.
พวกคุณไม่น้อยได้ทุ่มเทไปมากกับบทเรียนนี้
So I hope that you also got a lot of out this class.
ดังนั้นผมหวังว่าคุณจะได้รับประโยชน์จากบทเรียนนี้ไปมากเช่นกัน
And I wanted to say:
และผมอยากบอกว่า
Thank you very much for having been a student in this class.
ขอบคุณมากครับที่ได้เป็นนักศึกษาในบทเรียนนี้